Guide to the Barbara and Fred Whitehead Collection
The Wittliff Collections
Barbara and Fred Whitehead Collection
circa1970 - 1992
The Wittliff Collections
Whitehead, Barbara Mathews; Whitehead, Fred, 1937-1992
SWWC.024
4 boxes 19 woodblocks, 18 prints
4 Linear Feet 1 document box; 3 small newspaper boxes; individual posters in mapcases and framed artifact storage
The collection contains several woodcuts and posters from Whitehead and Whitehead Publishing Services.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Barbara and Fred Whitehead and Bill and Sally Wittliff, 1989-1991
Biographical Note
Fred and Barbara Whitehead's Whitehead and Whitehead Publishing Services provided artwork for book and poster illustrations as well as consultation on book production and design. Barbara Whitehead executed the designs while Fred Whitehead, also an artist, tended to the business end of the enterprise. Barbara Whitehead began her career as an illustrator in 1969 for Bill Wittliff's Encino Press after graduating from the University of Texas with a Master of Book Arts. The Whiteheads together also provided services for other Austin fine book printers David Lindsey, Thomas W. Taylor, and David Holman. Their designs have been used by the university presses of the University of Texas, Southern Methodist University and Texas Christian University. The Texas Institute of Letters granted Whitehead and Whitehead design awards twice: in 1982 for Journey to Pleasant Hill and in 1983 for Barbara Whitehead's book illustrations of R. G. Vliet's Clem Maverick. Fred Whitehead passed away July 1993 but Barbara Whitehead continues the business.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains posters, woodblocks and woodblock prints all by Barbara Whitehead. The prints include illustrations of works such as The Good Old Boys by Elmer Kelton, Clem Maverick by R. G. Vliet and The Grands by Carolyn Osborn. See also the Jan Reid papers, Accession number 92-136 for the bookjacket from Redneck Rock designed by Barbara Whitehead, and Accession No. 93-029 and 93-190 for the files on The Grands illustrated by Barbara Whitehead. For further information on the Whiteheads, see The Grands by Carolyn Osborn especially the introduction by Richard Holland and William D. Wittliff and the Encino Press, a bibliography compiled by Gould Whaley.
Artists -- Texas; Arts -- Texas; Wood-engraving; Art; Book design; Whitehead, Barbara Mathews; Whitehead, Fred, 1937-1992
- Montezuma Alley woodcut, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Two posters featuring three fish and a quote advertising Whitehead & Whitehead Book Publishers' Services, one annual broadside for the Book Club of Texas, various Barbara Whitehead prints including two of Sam Houston, two of Charles Goodnight, and two of J. Frank Dobie. All prints embossed Encino Press, undated
- Woodcut of skeletal figures, one pointing a gun at another, red annotations. Reverse side features a woodcut of a nude female figure sitting beneath a tree, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Women and Oxen woodcut, reverse side is a woodcut of a child's toy block with apples and letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Title woodblock from Maveric Crew: The Life and Death of Country Music Singer by R.G. Vliet, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Woodcut featuring a mule head and fence with text reading, "Trade in your old mule for new," on one side and, "Hot biscuits and soughum molasses," on the reverse, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Woodblocks for Southwestern Writers Collection doors, eleven prints for The Grands by Carolyn Olson, woodblock print for the poster celebrating Cabeza de Vaca week at SWTSU, (two versions), April 15, 1991
- The Good Old Boys title woodblock by Barbara Whitehead; reverse side features a snake and an eagle, circa 1985 (Box 2)
- Seashells woodblock; reverse side has additional shells and a pair of birds (Box 2)
- Prose fiction of the Cuban Revolution by Seymour Wenton title woodblock; reverse side features "A Christmas Thought", circa 1975 (Box 2)
- Carrasco by Wilson McKinney title woodblock; reverse features a village scene and drums, circa 1975 (Box 3)
- Santa Claus and the Bike, woodblock; reverse features an airplane, car, floral design, and male and female symbols (Box 3)
- Wood Stove and Pipe woodblcok; reverse side features a tree, music notes in a pot, and a pie (Box 3)
- Butterflies; reverse side features man with a gun and a field (Box 4)
- Hear's Looking at You, Kid; reverse side features multiple images including a karate robe, first aid kit, grave marker "EWP," hourglass, dollar signs, and a snowflake, among others (Box 4)
- Maverick Crew: by R.G. Vliet. Annotated "Vliet" in pencil: Woodcut of a group of musicians plus a guitar and a microphone stand; reverse side features an unrelated image of two people (Box 4)
- Maverick Crew: Woodblocks by Barbara Whitehead for R.G. Vliet's Clem Maverick. Illustrations of a band with a guitar, fiddle, and banjo players; reverse side features oil derricks and a Royal typewriter, circa 1983 (Box 4)